# Luiz Max Fagundes de Carvalho

lmax.fgv@gmail.com

School of Applied Mathematics (EMAp), Getúlio Vargas Foundation, Brazil.

Last update: May 2020

### Summary

Natural biological processes emit signals, which are often too "high" or too "low" for us to "hear". My goal as a scientist is to develop and apply statistical and mathematical tools to decode and quantify these biological signals. I hope a better understanding of these entities can lead to a progressive reduction of the world's disease burden. Bringing state-of-the-art statistical practice to the Life Sciences has been a major focus of my career in recent years. My interests lie in **Biostatistics**, ranging from complex networks to spatial analysis to statistical phylogenetics.

As you will notice if you continue reading, I am a big fan of collaboration, interacting with colleagues around Brazil and abroad. My current interests are:

- Bayesian inference of deterministic models;
- Combining (pooling) probability distributions;
- Phylogeny estimation: MCMC exploration of time-tree space characterising time-tree space, new transition kernels;
- Coupling mathematical models to coalescent-based population reconstructions;

Please feel free to contact me if your interests lie anywhere near these topics.

Google Scholar: https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=y2mxpbcAAAAJ&hl=en

Currículo Lattes: http://lattes.cnpq.br/7282202947621572

PDFs of my publications can be found at https://github.com/maxbiostat/papers/tree/master/PAPERS

### **Publications**

## Published/Accepted – peer reviewed

- [1] F. P. Camara, A. L. Gomes, Carvalho, L. M., and L. G. Castello, "Dynamic behavior of sylvatic yellow fever in Brazil (1954-2008)," Rev. Soc. Bras. Med. Trop., vol. 44, no. 3, pp. 297–299, 2011.
- [2] <u>Carvalho, L. M.</u> and F. P. Camara, "Epidemiological aspects of acquired immunodeficiency syndrome in older Brazilians: a comparative approach," *Braz J Infect Dis*, vol. 16, no. 1, pp. 34–37, 2012.
- [3] F. P. Camara, Carvalho, L. M., and A. L. Gomes, "Demographic profile of sylvatic yellow fever in Brazil from 1973 to 2008," Trans. R. Soc. Trop. Med. Hyg., vol. 107, pp. 324–327, May 2013.
- [4] <u>Carvalho, L. M.</u>, L. B. Santos, N. R. Faria, and W. de Castro Silveira, "Phylogeography of foot-and-mouth disease virus serotype O in Ecuador," *Infect. Genet. Evol.*, vol. 13, pp. 76–88, Jan 2013.
- [5] F. Bielejec, P. Lemey, <u>Carvalho, L. M.</u>, G. Baele, A. Rambaut, and M. A. Suchard, "Ï€BUSS: a parallel BEAST/BEAGLE utility for sequence simulation under complex evolutionary scenarios," BMC Bioinformatics, vol. 15, p. 133, 2014.
- [6] D. Mir, H. Romero, <u>Carvalho, L. M.</u>, and G. Bello, "Spatiotemporal dynamics of DENV-2 Asian-American genotype lineages in the Americas," *PLoS ONE*, vol. 9, no. 6, p. e98519, 2014.
- [7] F. C. Coelho and <u>Carvalho, L. M.</u>, "Estimating the attack ratio of dengue epidemics under time-varying force of infection using aggregated notification data," *Scientific reports*, vol. 5, 2015.
- [8] A. Rambaut, T. T. Lam, <u>Carvalho, L. M.</u>, and O. G. Pybus, "Exploring the temporal structure of heterochronous sequences using tempest (formerly Path-O-Gen)," *Virus Evolution*, vol. 2, no. 1, p. vew007, 2016.
- [9] A. Rambaut, G. Dudas, <u>Carvalho, L. M.</u>, D. J. Park, N. L. Yozwiak, E. C. Holmes, and K. G. Andersen, "Comment on "mutation rate and genotype variation of Ebola virus from Mali case sequences"," *Science*, vol. 353, no. 6300, pp. 658–658, 2016.
- [10] C. Codeço, D. Villela, M. F. Gomes, L. Bastos, O. Cruz, C. Struchiner, <u>Carvalho, L. M.</u>, and F. Coelho, "Zika is not a reason for missing the Olympic Games in Rio de Janeiro: response to the open letter of Dr Attaran and colleagues to Dr Margaret Chan, director-general, WHO, on the Zika threat to the Olympic and Paralympic Games," *Memórias do Instituto Oswaldo Cruz*, vol. 111, no. 6, pp. 414–415, 2016.
- [11] W. E. Diehl, A. E. Lin, N. D. Grubaugh, <u>Carvalho, L. M.</u>, K. Kim, P. P. Kyawe, S. M. McCauley, E. Donnard, A. Kucukural, P. McDonel, <u>et al.</u>, "Ebola virus glycoprotein with increased infectivity dominated the 2013–2016 epidemic," <u>Cell</u>, vol. 167, no. 4, pp. 1088–1098, 2016.
- [12] F. C. Coelho, B. Durovni, V. Saraceni, C. Lemos, C. T. Codeco, S. Camargo, <u>Carvalho, L. M.</u>, L. Bastos, D. Arduini, D. A. Villela, et al., "Higher incidence of Z'ika in adult women than adult men in Rio de Janeiro suggests a significant contribution of sexual transmission from men to women," *International Journal of Infectious Diseases*, vol. 51, pp. 128–132, 2016.

- [13] D. A. Villela, L. Bastos, <u>Carvalho, L. M.</u>, O. G. Cruz, M. F. Gomes, B. Durovni, M. C. Lemos, V. Saraceni, F. C. Coelho, and C. T. Codeco, "Zika in Rio de Janeiro: Assessment of basic reproduction number and comparison with dengue outbreaks," *Epidemiology and Infection*, pp. 1–9, 2017.
- [14] G. Dudas, Carvalho, L. M., T. Bedford, A. J. Tatem, G. Baele, N. R. Faria, D. J. Park, J. T. Ladner, A. Arias, D. Asogun, et al., "Virus genomes reveal factors that spread and sustained the Ebola epidemic," Nature, vol. 544, no. 7650, pp. 309–315, 2017.
- [15] G. Dudas, Carvalho, L. M., A. Rambaut, and T. Bedford, "MERS-CoV spillover at the camelhuman interface," eLife, vol. 7, p. e31257, 2018.
- [16] L. R. Vasconcellos, <u>Carvalho, L. M.</u>, I. Gonçalves, F. Coelho, F. Silveira, T. A. Silva, L. S. Bastos, M. Sorgine, L. Reis, F. Dias, C. J. Struchiner, F. Gazos-Lopes, and A. Hampshire, "Natural infection by the protozoan leptomonas wallacei impacts the morphology, physiology, reproduction, and lifespan of the insect oncopeltus fasciatus," *Scientific Reports*, 2019.
- [17] L. B. L. Santos, <u>Carvalho, Luiz Max</u>, W. Seron, F. C. Coelho, E. E. Macau, M. G. Quiles, and A. M. Monteiro, "How do urban mobility (geo) graph's topological properties fill a map?," *Applied Network Science*, vol. 4, no. 1, pp. 1–14, 2019.
- [18] M. Karcher, M. A. Suchard, G. Dudas, <u>Carvalho, L. M.</u>, and V. Minin, "Estimating effective population size changes from preferentially sampled genetic sequences," *PLoS Computational Biology*, 2020.
- [19] R. P. Niquini, R. M. Lana, A. G. Pacheco, O. G. Cruz, F. C. Coelho, <u>Carvalho, Luiz Max</u>, D. A. M. Villela, M. F. d. C. Gomes, and L. S. Bastos, "Description and comparison of demographic characteristics and comorbidities in SARI from COVID-19, SARI from Influenza, and the Brazilian general population," *Cadernos de Saúde Pública*, vol. 36, p. e00149420, 2020.

### Under review

- [20] Carvalho, Luiz Max and J. G. Ibrahim, "On the properties of the normalised power prior," arXiv preprint arXiv:2004.14912, 2020.
- [21] F. C. Coelho, L. M. Carvalho, R. M. Lana, O. G. Cruz, L. S. Bastos, C. T. Codeco, M. F. Gomes, and D. Villela, "Modeling the post-containment elimination of transmission of COVID-19," medRxiv, 2020.
- [22] Carvalho, Luiz Max, N. R. Faria, G. König, M. A. Suchard, P. Lemey, W. d. C. Silveira, and G. Baele, "Spatio-temporal dynamics of foot-and-mouth disease virus in South America," arXiv preprint arXiv:1505.01105, 2020.
- [23] R. Kubinec and Carvalho, Luiz Max, "A retrospective Bayesian model for measuring covariate effects on observed COVID-19 test and case counts," SocArXiv preprint, 2020.

## Conference papers

[24] Carvalho, L.M., L. Santos, P. Pereira, and W. Silveira, "Phylodynamics of foot-and-mouth disease virus: a complex network approach," in *Proceedings of the 10th Brazilian Conference on Dynamics, Control and Their Applications*, Brazilian Society for Applied and Computational Mathematics, 2011.

### Book chapters

- [25] F. Camara and Carvalho, L. M., "Febres Hemorrágicas virais [Viral hemorrhagic fevers]," in *Introdução à Virologia Humana* (N. Santos, M. T. Romanos, and M. D. Wigg, eds.), Rio de Janeiro: Guanabara Koogan, 3rd ed., 2014.
- [26] Carvalho, L. M., "Métodos bayesianos para inferir o padrão de dispersão de agentes patogénicos : filogeografia do vírus da febre aftosa na América do Sul como um caso de estudo [Bayesian methods to infer spread patterns for pathogens: the phylogeography of Foot-and-Mouth Disease virus in South America as a case study]," in Abordagens Moleculares em Veterinária (M. V. Cunha and J. Inácio, eds.), Lisbon: Lidel Editora, 1st ed., 2014.
- [27] <u>Carvalho, L. M.</u>, C. Struchiner, and L. Bastos, "Bayesian inference of deterministic population growth models," in *Interdisciplinary Bayesian Statistics* (A. Polpo de Campos, F. Neto, L. Ramos-Rifo, J. Stern, and M. Lauretto, eds.), vol. 118, pp. 217–228, Springer Verlag, 1st ed., 2015.

### Tech reports

[28] C. Codeço, D. Villela, F. Coelho, L. Bastos, <u>Carvalho, LM</u>, M. Gomes, O. Cruz, and R. Lana, "Risco de espalhamento da covid-19 em populações indígenas: considerações preliminares sobre vulnerabilidade geográfica e socioeconômica," *Rio de Janeiro: Fiocruz: FGV*, vol. 18, 2020.

## Work in progress<sup>1</sup>

L. Zimmermann, <u>Carvalho, L.M.</u>, L. Vasconcellos, L. Bastos, C. Struchiner, and A. H. Lopes, "Temperature-dependent oviposition and egg eclosion of Chagas disease vector *Rhodnius prolixus*", In preparation.

<u>Carvalho, L.M.</u>, D.A. Vilella, F.C. Coelho, L. Bastos, "On the choice of the weights for the logarithmic pooling of probability distributions", In preparation.

Carvalho, L.M., G. Baele, M.A. Suchard, A. Rambaut, "An efficient, tunable time-tree transition kernel for Bayesian phylogenetics", In preparation.

Carvalho, L.M., Dudas, G., Stadler, T., Rambaut, A., Bedford, T. "Bayesian estimation of  $R_0$  from sub-critical chains of transmission under observation error", In preparation.

Gillespie, C., <u>Carvalho, L.M.</u>, "A complete-data framework for fitting power-law distributions", In preparation.

 $<sup>^{1}\</sup>mathrm{Drafts}$  in final phase of preparation

### Education

2009–2012 | BSc (hons.) Microbiology and Immunology, Federal University of Rio de Janeiro,

Brazil.

2014–2018 PhD Evolutionary Biology, University of Edinburgh, UK.

Thesis committee: Richard Everitt (Reading) and Jarrod Hadfield (Edinburgh).

### **Professional Experience**

2010–2013 | Pan American Health Organization (PAHO)

Position: Statistical Assistant

Role: Developed and analysed quality control experiments for veterinary diagnos-

tic tests;

Research on Foot-and-Mouth Disease virus (FMDV) phylodynamics

### Academic Experience

2009–2011 | Infectious Diseases Epidemiology Division (SEDI), Institute of Microbiology, Fed-

eral University of Rio de Janeiro

Position: Scientific initiation student

Supervisor: Prof. Dr. Fernando Portela Câmara

Role: research on the epidemiology of AIDS, sylvatic yellow fever and dengue.

2012–2013 | Programme for Scientific Computing (PROCC), Oswaldo Cruz Foundation

(Fiocruz)

Position: Scientific initiation student

Supervisor: Prof. Dr. Oswaldo Gonçalves Cruz

Role: research on spatial partition methods for health areal data.

2013–2014 Programme for Scientific Computing (PROCC), Oswaldo Cruz Foundation

(Fiocruz)

Position: Scientific initiation student

Supervisors: Prof. Dr. Claudio Struchiner and Dr. Leonardo Bastos

Role: research on Bayesian inference of deterministic population growth models,

multilevel binary regression and opinion pooling.

2014–2018 Institute of Evolutionary Biology (SBS), University of Edinburgh

Position: PhD student

Supervisors: Andrew Rambaut and Darren Obbard

Role: research on statistical phylogenetics methods for RNA virus phylodynamics.

2018–2019 Programme for Scientific Computing (PROCC) and National School of Public

Health (ENSP), Oswaldo Cruz Foundation

Position: Postdoctoral Researcher Supervisor: Claudio Struchiner

Role: research on statistical methods applied to Public Health.

2020 School of Applied Mathematics (EMAp), Getúlio Vargas Foundation (FGV)

Position: Lecturer

Role: research on Biostatistics and teaching Statistics at the graduate and under-

graduate levels.

#### Conferences<sup>2</sup>

#### Presented work

- 2009 Gomes, A.L.B.B; Carvalho, L.M.; Camara, F.P. Dinâmica Espacial da Dengue no Rio de Janeiro: 1986 a 2009 [Spatial dynamics of dengue in Rio de Janeiro: 1986 to 2009], 2009, II International Congress on Geography of Health, Uberlândia -MG, Brazil.
- Vianez Jr., J.L.; <u>Carvalho, L. M.</u>; Bisch, P. **Development of a workflow for large-scale epitope prediction: dengue virus as a study of case**. In: X Meeting 2011, 2011, Florianópolis–SC, Brazil. X Meeting 2011 Abstract Book, 2011. v. ID 234.
- 2011 Carvalho, L.M.; Santos, L.B.; Silveira, W.C. Phylodynamics of Foot-and-Mouth Disease Virus: a Complex Network approach. XXII Meeting of the Brazilian Society of Virology, Águas de Lindóia – SP, Brazil.
- 2012 <u>Carvalho, L. M.</u>; Santos, L.B.; Faria, N.R.; Silveira, W.C. **Phylogeographic Dynamics of foot-and-mouth disease virus in Ecuador 2002 to 2010**, 2012 In 17th International BioInformatics Workshop on Virus Evolution and Molecular Epidemiology, Belgrade, Serbia.
- 2012 Carvalho, L.M.; Faria, N.R.; Silveira, W.C. Phylodynamics of Foot-and-Mouth Disease Virus in South America: a Comprehensive Analysis. XXIII Brazilian Congress of Virology, Foz do Iguaçu – PR, Brazil.
- Vasconcellos, L.R.C.; Dias, F.A.; Soares, J. B. R. C.; <u>Carvalho, L. M.</u>; Oliveira, M. M.; Alves e Silva, T. L.; Gonçalves, I.; Oliveira, M. F.; Lopes, F.G.; Lopes, A. H. C. S. Interaction of the hemipteran Oncopeltus fasciatus with the trypanosomatid Leptomonas wallacei: an insight into parasitism. In: Gordon Research Conference on Biology of Host-Parasite Interactions, 2012, Newport, RI, USA. Annals of the Gordon Research Conference on Biology of Host-Parasite Interactions, 2012. v. 1. p. 1-2.
- Zimmermann, L.T.; <u>Carvalho, L.M.</u>; Vasconcellos, L.R.; Bastos, L.S.; Struchiner, C.J.; Lopes, A.H. <u>Temperature-dependent oviposition and egg eclosion of Chagas disease vector *Rhodnius prolixus* In XXIX Annual Meeting of the Brazilian Society of Protozoology, 2013, Caxambu-MG, Brazil. Abstract book of the XXIX Annual Meeting of the SBPz, p. 159, ID V004.</u>
- 2014 Carvalho, L. M.; Struchiner, C.J.; Bastos, L.S. Bayesian inference of deterministic population growth models In XII Brazilian Meeting on Bayesian Statistics (EBEB), 2014, Atibaia-SP, Brazil. Abstract book of the XII Brazilian Meeting on Bayesian Statistics, p. 63
- Bastos, L. S.; <u>Carvalho, L. M.</u> Random Effects Binary Model with Misclassified Response In Joint Statistical Meetings, 2014, Boston MS, USA.

<sup>&</sup>lt;sup>2</sup>Main conferences I have attended to or had work presented at. For a complete list please visit my Lattes CV.

#### Participated

- 2012 VIII Brazilian Congress of Epidemiology, São Paulo-SP, Brazil.
- 2013 | 1st Symposium on Big Data and Public Health, Rio de Janeiro-RJ, Brazil.

#### **Invited Talks**

- 2011 Phylodynamics of Foot-and-Mouth Disease Virus: a Complex Network approach.
  XXII Meeting of the Brazilian Society of Virology
- 2011 Playing Dumb: The Misuse of Statistics in Biology. Institute of Microbiology, Federal University of Rio de Janeiro.
- 2012 Knowledge Discovery in Databases through Complex Networks: application to phylodynamics. WaFIS 2012
- 2014 Bayesian inference of deterministic population growth models. XII Brazilian Meeting on Bayesian Statistics
- 2015 Phylodynamics: how Genetics and Mathematics are changing our understanding of infectious diseases. 30rd Brazilian Mathematics Colloquium
- 2015 Choosing the weights for the logarithmic pooling of probability distributions. 60th World Statistics Congress.
- 2016 On the choice of the weights for the logarithmic pooling of probability distributions. XIII Brazilian Meeting on Bayesian Statistics.
- 2019 Recent advances in the phylodynamics of infectious diseases. Institute of Microbiology, Federal University of Rio de Janeiro.
- On the choice of weights for logarithmic pooling of probability distributions. School of Applied Mathematics, Getúlio Vargas Foundation .
- 2020 Modelando a COVID-19: extraindo o máximo de dados ruins. School of Applied Mathematics, Getúlio Vargas Foundation.
- 2020 Efficient brute-force marginalisation of discrete variables in an epidemic model of sub-critical transmission. StanCon2020.
- 2020 Adaptive Markov chain Monte Carlo on the space of time-calibrated trees. 14th International Conference in Monte Carlo & Quasi-Monte Carlo Methods in Scientific Computing (MCQMC 2020).

### Memberships

 $Brazilian \ Statistical \ Association \ (ABE), \ Analytical \ Methods \ in \ Epidemiological \ Surveillance \ Group \ (MAVE).$ 

### Teaching Experience

2007–2011 | High School Chemistry and Biology

I was a voluntary teacher of whole-year high school courses on organic chemistry, general chemistry and biology.

2010–2013 Basics of Mathematics and Statistics for Microbiology

Federal University of Rio de Janeiro

Supervisor: Prof. Dr. Fernando Portela Câmara

Basic calculus; descriptive statistics, Gaussian distribution and hypothesis testing.

2010 | Topics in Human Physiology

Federal University of Rio de Janeiro

Supervisor: Prof. Dr. Pedro Paulo Elsas

By means of seminars and group discussions, we approach particular aspects of human physiology and stimulate the students to draw general conclusions about the subjacent biological processes.

2012 Bioinformatics

Federal University of Rio de Janeiro

Supervisor: Prof. Andrew Macrae, PhD

Basics on Bioinformatics: basic genome annotation, databases, alignment, phylogenetics.

2014-2017 | Molecular Evolution

University of Edinburgh

Supervisor: Prof. Andrew Rambaut, PhD

Molecular phylogenetics.

2017 Statistics for Genetics

University of Edinburgh Supervisor: Ian White TA in the Bayesian module

2020- Statistical inference

School of Applied Mathematics (EMAp)

Undegraduate course (60 hours).

2020- Computational Statistics

School of Applied Mathematics (EMAp)

PhD course (45 hours).

#### Awards

2010 Honourable Mention - XVI Week of Microbiology and Immunology, Federal University of Rio de Janeiro.

2011 Honourable Mention - XVII Week of Microbiology and Immunology, Federal University of Rio de Janeiro.

2011 Selected for Oral presentation – XXII National Meeting of the Brazilian Society for Virology.

2012 Honourable Mention - XVIII Week of Microbiology and Immunology.

2014 | Selected for Oral presentation – XII Brazilian Meeting on Bayesian Statistics.

2014 Principal's Career Development Scholarship, University of Edinburgh.

## Languages

Portuguese Native

English | Fluent (CAE – Grade A)

Spanish Advanced

# References

Reference	What for	email
Prof. Dr. Fernando Portela Câmara	Research and Teaching	fp3camara@yahoo.com.br
Prof. Ângela Hampshire Lopes, PhD	Research	angela.lopes@micro.ufrj.br
Prof. Andrew Macrae, PhD	Teaching	amacrae@biologia.ufrj.br
Prof. Dr. Pedro Paulo Xavier Elsas	Teaching	pxelsas@micro.ufrj.br
Prof. Claudio Struchiner, PhD	Research and Teaching	stru@fiocruz.br
Leonardo Bastos, PhD	Research	lsbastos@fiocruz.br
Prof. Philippe Lemey, PhD	Research	philippe.lemey@rega.kuleuven.be
Prof. Flavio Codeço Coelho, PhD	Research	fccoelho@fgv.br
Prof. Andrew Rambaut, PhD	Research and Teaching	a.rambaut@ed.ac.uk
Jarrod Hadfield, PhD	Research	j.hadfield@ed.ac.uk
Prof. Richard Everitt, PhD	Research	richard.g.everitt@gmail.com